Guide to the Plácido Vega Papers, 1855-1864
Department of Special Collections
- (December, 1862) (Box 8, Folder 93)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from B. Peraza (results of attempts to enlist men); from J. Gaxiola, on same subject; report from J. Aguiluz (efforts to secure supplies); from Carlos E. Norton (intentions of French to attack Puebla following February); from J. Rojo, Jesús Vega (reference to R. Meza); from Manuel E. Rodríguez, editor of La voz de Mexico; from R. Urrea (account of attack upon Hacienda dé Dolores directed by Arzapalo in November; personal motives suspected); from J. Mugarrieta, A. Aragón (attack on hacienda); from Carlos Norton, informing Plácido Vega of movements of French, who disembarked at Veracruz with force of 23,000 men in plan to attack capital; from J. Arzapalo (November, 1862), giving account of attack upon hacienda; from Felipe Máxime (November, 1862), making report concerning acquisition of supplies; from M. Tirado, I. Isabal, C. Palomares (November, 1862), giving report of his actions; from Q. Douglas (actions taken; plans); from I. Pesquiera, J. García Morales, R. Robertson of United States consulate, asking for appointment for C. H. Poor, captain of ship Saranac; from M. Delgado, B. Silva (developments); from other officials, supporters. Letters from Plácido Vega to Manuel E. Rodríguez, J. Mugarrieta, A. Aragón (Hacienda de Dolores); to M. Delgado, R. Félix y Buelna, C. Norton (measures taken in Sinaloa to support Federal government in resisting French); to J. Arzapalo (Hacienda de Dolores); to Felipe Máxime, B. Silva, I. Isabal, Q. Douglas, I. Pesquiera, J. García Morales, R. Robertson, M. Delgado, to other officials, supporters.
- (December, 1862; January, 1863) (Box 8, Folder 94)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from Felipe Arellano, M. Figueroa, M. E. Rodríguez, F. Cortés (protest by French consul concerning shipment of arms; hope for favorable settlement of concern of United States consul, Robertson); from others requesting payment of sums owed, reporting information, etc. Letters from Plácido Vega to L. Angulo, Jesus Lopez Portillo, governor of Jalisco, telling of Vega's intention to send his representative, Apolonio Ángulo, to M. Doblado to inform him of situation in Sinaloa; letters from Plácido Vega to M. Figueroa, J. Mugarrieta, M. E. Rodríguez. Paper authorizing payment of sum to I. Maldonado, payment of other debts.
- (January, February, 1863) (Box 8, Folder 95)
  Military reports by Juan Álvarez; list of those to receive sums of money from government; reports by F. Cortés, others. Report by Plácido Vega to M. Doblado; other official statements by Plácido Vega, others. Official papers from state of Guerrero. Financial statement submitted to Plácido Vega by I.R.Moller. Letters to Plácido Vega from I. Isabal (January, 1863); from M. Romero (statement sent by Moller); from Camilo Vega, Jesús Vega, E. Lamberg, D. Alvarez (receipt of instructions); from J. Álvarez, R. Félix y Buelna, J. Lopez Portillo, Thomas Corwin, on behalf of R. Robertson (reference to A. Angulo). Letters from Plácido Vega to I. Isabal (February, 1863); to J. García Morales (February, 1863); to Juan Kelly, Colonel I. Ortiz, F. Cortés; to C. Ramos, R. Solís, E. Lamberg, and M. García, informing them of Plácido Vega's intention to take brigade to Acapulco; letters from Plácido Vega to Benito Juárez, I. Comonfort, J. González Ortega (plans); to J. Mugarrieta, J. Álvarez (reference to mission of A. Ángulo); to Camilo Vega, suggesting candidates for offices; to Jesús Vega (political, military); to A. Ángulo, R. Félix y Buelna (plans to go to capital at request of Benito Juárez; to J. García Morales (developments).
- (March, 1863) (Box 8, Folder 96)
  Statements by E. Lamberg concerning military moves; military notes by Rafael Solís (intelligence concerning French war ships). Statements concerning ships by P. Carmona, prefect of district of Acapulco. Lists of soldiers ailing sent Plácido Vega by Carmona. Statements by J. Álvarez concerning military plans; orders from Benito Juárez concerning meeting of attack upon Puebla by French. Statement by J. Álvarez reporting arrival of Plácido Vega at Acapulco with division from Sinaloa (J. García Morales acting as governor). Statement from D. Álvarez, governor of state of Guerrero, reporting on situation in region. Reports by General Vicente Jiménez, others; messages from Ministry of War. Instructions from Plácido Vega to F. Cortés. Letters to Plácido Vega from E. Lamberg, reporting on matters, outlining plans; from R. del Valle (Tepic; recommendations concerning appointments).
- (February, March, 1863) (Box 8, Folder 97)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from P. Ogazón (military plans; reference to Márquez); from L. Angulo (political, military matters; reference to Corona, Doblado, others); from D. Álvarez, J. Álvarez (military matters); from V. Jiménez (military matters); from M. E. Rodriguez, General Miguel García, Pedro Narvarete (Navarte)?; from A. Cruz, Juan Kelly (reference to French ships); from Benito Juárez, concerning Corona; from F. Cortés, R. Félix y Buelna. Letters from Plácido Vega to José Iribarren (financial matters); to A. Ángulo (reference to Doblado, military matters); to P. Ogazón (reference to French ships at Acapulco); to L. Ángulo, D. Alvarez (reference to Haller, etc.); to J. García Morales, F. Merino (French ships); to prefect of Sinaloa (instructions); to A. Villaverde, J. Arzapalo (Puebla surrounded by French; plans); to V. Jiménez, F. Cortés, J. Álvarez (campaign near Puebla); to A. Cruz, Benito Juárez (report on military situation; political matters; appointment of Corona as Comandante Militar of Sonora, Sinaloa; Plácido Vega's fears concerning Corona). Circular letters from Plácido Vega to prefects of various districts of Sinaloa and to captains stationed in these districts, informing them of military situation in country and of appointment by Doblado of Corona as commander in Sonora and Sinaloa.
- (April, 1863) (Box 9, Folder 98)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from P. Ogazón (developments; reference to Márquez); from L. Ángulo (political; reference to Doblado, Corona); from F. Cortés, J. García Morales, others. Letters from Plácido Vega to José Nuñez (needs of division); to Jesus Castañeda (needs of division); to J. García Morales (developments); to Benito Juárez (condemnation of Márquez, praise of J. García Morales; recommendation of latter for post of governor of Sinaloa); letters from Plácido Vega to other officials, supporters. Telegrams sent to Plácido Vega by Pedro Arce, informing him of arrival of J. García Morales at capital and by Manuel Gómez, asking Plácido Vega to see him. Statements authorizing payment of debts; statements by Minister of War pertaining to military orders; statements of maneuvers executed, military plans, needs. Statements sent by Plácido Vega to Minister of Labor concerning action taken by Plácido Vega to make tillable land available to workers. Statements sent by Plácido Vega to Minister of Foreign Relations concerning aid rendered by foreign citizens. Statement concerning conduct of individuals. Statements sent Treasury Department (Minister of Treasury). Note from I. Comonfort.
- (May, 1863) (Box 9, Folder 99)
  Copies of pamphlet dated May 30, 1863, constituting exposé of differences between Plácido Vega and Ramón Corona. Pamphlet traces development of differences during years 1861-1863; records reaction of Plácido Vega and followers to proclamation issued in March, 1863, by R. Corona during absence of Plácido Vega from Mazatlán. Letters to Plácido Vega from General Jiménez (developments in other parts of Mexico; reference to Haller). Copy of letter sent by Jiménez to Coronel A. Villaverde. Letters to Plácido Vega from P. Navarte [?] (local developments); from D. Álvarez (return of F. Cortés from San Francisco with supplies; capture of fort at Puebla by French); from M. Carillo, I. Weston, seeking to buy land as speculation from Plácido Vega; from M. Delgado, Antonio Vejar (payment of sum); from General A. Cruz, M. Blanco, J. Vasavilbaso, deputy; from F. Cortés, J. Castáneda (financial obligation); from B. Almada, deputy (Corona); from E. Lamberg (military matters; concern over central army, political influence); from J. Domingo Cortés, Pedro Váldez, Ignacio Orozco (annoyance with central army for inaction; reference to Comonfort); from M. Degollado, I. Comonfort, J. Casanova (including clipping, article by F. Zarco defending Plácido Vega against Corona); from Benito Juárez (Comonfort); from J. Álvarez. Letters from Plácido Vega to V. Jiménez, P. Navarte, I. Weston, Joaquín Vega (action of Corona); to J. García Morales, F. Ferrel (reference to Márquez, Corona, Norton, Kelly, others); to Antonio Vejar, Jesús Vega (letter from C. Palomares to R. Félix y Buelna); to Benito Juárez (plans; lack of funds); to A. Cruz, Camilo Vega (political); to F. Chávez (political); to Clemente Espinosa de los Monteros, F. Ávilez, R. Félix y Buelna (Márquez, Corona); additional letters to Jesús Vega (Márquez; shift in political influence; efforts to refute claims of Corona); letters from Plácido Vega to M. Blanco, A. Villaverde, J. Castaeda, F. Cortés, B. Almada, Juan de la Fuente (Corona); to E. Lamberg (instructions); to Minister of Treasury, I. Comonfort, Benito Juárez (political, administrative matters); to Pedro Valdez, Ignacio Orozco, J. Álvarez, others.
- (May, 1863) (Box 9, Folder 100)
  Letters from Plácido Vega to Manuel E. Rodríguez, A. Cruz, J. García Morales. Statement of need for funds for supplies for army, on march. Instructions to Valdez, Iribarren, Villaverde; official statements concerning troops movements; instructions to Captain Arcadio Vega. Statement concerning financial transaction, by Comonfort. List of matters to be discussed with central government. Lists of ill among soldiers; lists of supplies; lists of instructions from central government to Plácido Vega. Telegrams to Placido Vega from various officials. Statements by Joaquín Vega, Juan Álvarez, concerning arms, supplies, etc. Lists of officers, soldiers by battalion; lists of personnel promoted. Clipping: reprint of proclamation issued to inhabitants of Sinaloa by J. García Morales concerning political intentions of Colonel Antonio Rosales (May 14, 1863); appeal to people to support Plácido Vega.
- (June, 1863) (Box 9, Folder 101)
  Letters from Plácido Vega to Benito Juárez (customs house revenue); to J. Casanova (Kelly transaction); to B. Almada and J. Castañeda; to J. García Morales, J. Núñez (financial matters); to Apolonio Angulo, Juan Kelly, F. Cortés, Felipe Arellano (Camilo Rosas Landa). Letters to Plácido Vega from J. Núñez (Castaneda and Kelly). Papers concerning prisoner V. Aguirre. Statement concerning debt to Kelly. Statement by Porfirio Díaz concerning military orders.
- (July, 1863) (Box 9, Folder 102)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from M. Rubí (results of interview with Benito Juárez concerning R. Corona; reference to Saligny and his indignation with Mexico; to affairs in Puebla); from relatives of I. Zaragoza; from Porfirio Díaz, F. Ferrel, others. Letters from Plácido Vega to M. Romero, J. Kelly (debt); to Guillermo Prieto, J. Núñez (political, military); to A. Ángulo, Joe Aguirre, F. Zarco (ability of Zacatecas and Durango to aid central government; Patoni's return as governor); to R. Banda (plans); to Patoni and J. Toledo (military developments); to F. Ferrel, I. Comonfort (military developments); to P. Ogazón (military developments, plans); to León Ángulo, General José Arteaga (Doblado, other matters); to General Isidoro Ortiz, C. Palomares, Porfirio Díaz (military developments); to relatives of I. Zaragoza, other supporters.
- (August, 1863) (Box 9, Folder 103)
  Letter from Plácido Vega to F. Ferrel.
- (September, 1863) (Box 9, Folder 104)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from M. Castro, M. Rodríguez, Ignacio Isabal, B. Reyes, Camilo Vega (local political appointments); from M. Díaz Vera, Jesús Vega, I. Comonfort, F. Zarco, Joaquín Román, concerning Doblado; from S. Lerdo de Tejada, J. Castañeda (political matters); from M. Delgado, José Uraga (reference to Napoleon III; lamentations for country); from Clemente Espinosa de los Monteros, General Félix Berriozábal (reference to Juarez, other matters); from N.N. (August 22, 1863), mentioning confiscation of property in country, recall of Forey and Saligny, dissension among liberals, need to replace Doblado with more energetic leader, reference to Núñez as agent for Doblado, desire for new cabinet; letters to Plácido Vega from J. González Ortega, J. M. Patoni, others. Letters from Plácido Vega to G. Prieto (political); to J. González Ortega (reference to Lerdo de Tejada); to Camilo Vega, I. Comonfort, F. Zarco, Joaquín Román, S. Lerdo de Tejada (national politics); to J. Castañeda, José Uraga, General Félix Berriozábal, Manuel E. de Ortega, J. González Ortega; to N.N. (reorganization of cabinet; departure of Forey, Saligny; nomination of Maximillian); letters from Plácido Vega to J.M. Patoni (need for arms; inability of Norton to procure them in California; Vega's plans to go to California to attempt to obtain arms; intentions to leave government in hands of J. García Morales); letters to F. Ferrel, others. Statement by I. Arzapalo concerning administration of affairs in Mazatlán; statement by J. García Morales concerning Corona. Clipping from La opinión de Sinaloa concerning Rosales and attempted insurrection.
- (October, 1863) (Box 9, Folder 105)
  Letters from Plácido Vega to F. Tirado (Rosales and uprising): to R. Banda, F. Ferrel (administrative matters); to U. Lassepas (debt); to Comonfort, Porfirio Díaz (military, political); to I. Pesquiera (recommendations); to Jesús Vega, Buelna, José López Uraga (need for supplies, etc.); to Ramón de la Vega, in office of governor of Colima; to C. Palomares, Julio García, Manuel Rodríguez in San Francisco; to José Gaxiola (administrative matters); to I. Isabal. Second letter from Plácido Vega to Porfirio Díaz speaks of defeat of Corona's forces near Tepic by Lozada; refers to Corwin, to Juárez' decision to move government to San Luis Potosí. Letters from Plácido Vega to A. Ángulo, J.M.Patoni, P. Blancarte (administrative matters); to J. Arteaga (Corona); to L. Angulo (advice received concerning Corona and reconciliation). Letters to Plácido Vega from J. Sánchez (condemnation of Corona); from Camilo Vega, F. Tirado, R. Banda, U. Lassepas (payment of debt); from S. Lerdo de Tejada (views on government); from F. Chávez (political matters); from F. Ocampo, F. Miranda, Ramón Amarillas (political, military); from J. Toledo (developments, views); from F. Cortes (shipment of arms); from C. Palomares, I. Ortiz (departure from government of Doblado, protector of Corona); from Manuel Rodríguez in San Francisco; from J. Gaxiola, I. Isabal, P. Blancarte, J. Garcia Morales (Márquez, Corona, Doblado); from R. Félix y Buelna (developments); from B. Almada, others.
- (November, 1863) (Box 9, Folder 106)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from Manuel Rodríguez, José Nuñez, J. Castañeda, J. Arteaga (political developments); from J. Irbarren, Jesus Vega (developments); from E. Henry, A. Paredes, F. Arellano, I. Isabal, P. Navarte, J. Uraga (developments); from F. Zarco, I. Comonfort (cabinet and Doblado); from J. González Ortega (Doblado's resignation from cabinet); from General Agel Frías (military matters; Vega's projected trip to San Francisco); from Buelna. Letters from Plácido Vega to General A. Cruz, José Nuñez, A. Ávilez (instructions); to L. Ángulo (developments); to J. González Ortega (developments; desire to have Corona relieved of post); to Jesús Vega, A. Ángulo, C. Rosas Landa, Ramón Vega (enclosing copies of letters written by Plácido Vega to Benito Juárez, Porfirio Díaz, and General Uraga); letters from Plácido Vega to F. Berriozábal (recommendations made to Juárez); to J. Castaeda (reference to Doblado, other matters); to A. Carvajal, J. Arteaga, Jesús Vega, A. Paredes, B. Almada, S. Lerdo de Tejada, I. Isabal, M. Rojo, F. Zarco (Vega's projected trip to San Francisco); to I. Comonfort, A. Frías (outcome of local elections); to others. Invoice for goods received at Mazatlán. Receipt for sum of money from Kelly Company. Notice of yearly inventories and statistical reports to be filed, with aid of prefects. Statement supplying data needed by government in reference to Rafael López; statement certifying as to work (administrative) of F. Aragón in mine of Guadalupe de Ios Reyes; statement concerning funds, payment of sums.
- (December, 1863) (Box 9, Folder 107)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from R. Félix y Buelna, I. Isabal, C. Rosas Landa, M. Carillo, Ramón Vega (death of Comonfort); from J. Castañeda, E. Montes, A. Aragón (administrative matters); from Felipe Máxime, R. Banda, Jesús Vega (developments); from M.Maldonado, F. Cortés, P. Blancarte, A. Vega, others.
- (January, February, 1864) (Box 9, Folder 108)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from Isabal, including receipt signed by Arcadio Vega for sum received from Isabal; from B. Peraza, F. Sachez, F. Chávez, F. Prieto, (interview with Patoni); from Buelna (enlistment, appointments in certain districts); from B. Insunza, R. Cevallos, Joaquín Valdez, D. Rubí, G. Prieto, J. Mateos. Jesus Vega (results of talks with J. García Morales concerning pay, etc.); from Arcadio Vega, P. Navarte, others. Letters from Plácido Vega to M. Carillo, J. Castañeda, Ramón Vega, E. Montes, P. Navarte (intentions of Rosales, Márquez); to A. Aragón, Jesús Vega, M. Maldonado (reference to Uraga at capital and to Porfirio Díaz at Puebla); to P. Ogazón (reference to Napoleon III, etc.); to L. Ángulo, others. List of individuals to receive pamphlet concerning R. Corona. Letters from Plácido Vega to Isabal, F. Chávez (arms); to employees of prefectures; to F. Prieto, Buelna, B. Insunza, Patoni, G. Prieto (postponement of Vega's trip to San Francisco; developments); to J. Mateos, Arcadio Vega (financial matters). List of supplies acquired.
- (March, 1864) (Box 9, Folder 109)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from A. Frías (abandonment of San Luis Potosí by Federal government for Saltillo as headquarters; hope for greater co-operation with Washington; political, military developments; Napoleon III); from Arcadio Vega (receipt for sum received by Isabal); from A. Paez (administrative matters); from R. Banda, Joaquín Isabal, other officials, supporters. Letters from Plácido Vega to A. Frías, I. Isabal, Jesús Vega (financial matters); to R. Banda, others.
- (May, 1864) (Box 10, Folder 110)
  Letters of introduction for G. Clark sent officials by Plácido Vega in San Francisco. Statements by Plácido Vega in San Francisco pertaining to Kelly-Myrtle transaction. Clippings in English: articles reprinting proclamation by Juárez to citizens, setting forth new Articles; proclamation by Plácido Vega to inhabitants of Sinaloa, concerning new regulations pertaining to acquisition of land, new laws concerning foreigners, etc. Statement issued by Plácido Vega in San Francisco (May 4, 1864) to president of Junta Patriotica, giving appraisal of situation in Mexico derived from talks with governors and various officials of northern states (of Mexico). Letters from Plácido Vega in San Francisco to Kelly-Myrtle Company; to I. Pesquiera, officials of prefectures, etc., concerning matters attended to by Plácido Vega in San Francisco, including arrangements for arms, munitions, supplies to be sent to Mexico. Letters from Plácido Vega to Matías Romero, ambassador from Mexico to Washington, concerning representative, Dodge; to P. Ogazeón (administrative matters); to Buelna, Jésus Vega, others. Letters to Plácido Vega from J. Casanova, Parrodi, Lozada, others, setting forth their views. Clipping from La voz de Méjico (June 28), denouncing Lozada, others, as traitors. Clipping contains articles or reprints of letters, signed by Plácido Vega, others.
- (June, 1864) (Box 10, Folder 111)
  Letters to Plácido Vega in San Francisco from various supporters.
- (September, October, 1864) (Box 10, Folder 112)
  Statement by Plácido Vega concerning national elections in the United States; support for Lincoln. Letters from Plácido Vega to M. Romero in Washington; to P. Ramírez (article in La voz de Méjico); to R. Pacheco (reference to articles in Nuevo mundo and La voz de Méjico). Letters to Plácido Vega from R. Pacheco (support of Lincoln in the United States, Juárez in Mexico); from other officials in Mexico.
- (December, 1864) (Box 10, Folder 113)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from I. Lananaga in Mazatlán, giving Vega report of developments in Sinaloa and in Mexico. Letters from Plácido Vega to Fortunato to Vega (sum owed Sánchez); to Lerdo de Tejada (including copy of letter written by Plácido Vega to Benito Juárez concerning Mexican representatives to the United States.
  Letter from Plácido Vega to T. Brown, agent for United States Treasury Department. Statement of liquidation from R. Moller Company.
- (1860-1861) (Box 10, Folder 114)
  Documents pertaining to plot of A. Rosales. Note addressed to Plácido Vega by Rosales (1861). Letters to Plácido Vega from Domingo Cortés; articles from La opinion de Sinaloa; statement by F. Cortés concerning activities of A. Rosales, R. Meza, others (July, 1860).
- (1861-1862) (Box 10, Folder 115)
  Copies of proclamation issued by Plácido Vega as governor of Sinaloa (1862). Statement by E. Lamberg, including list of items, with cost of each, distributed to squadron of Sinaloa (1861). List of items lost or needed by battalion of Sinaloa. Receipt signed by Plácido Vega. List of sums owed to men of brigade; lists of other expenses, of revenues, of armaments distributed; financial statements for 1861; records for 1861.
- (1860-1863) (Box 10, Folder 116)
  Letters to José M. Gutiérrez from F. Parra; letters to Plácido Vega from R. Corona, R. Ocampo. Oficial statements by R. Corona (1863) concerning campaign at Tepic; statements by F. Ferrel concerning imprisonment of Dávalos. Instructions issued by government concerning R. Corona, others (1863). Additional papers concerning activities of Corona at Tepic. List of sums owed brigade of Sinaloa. Statements by Corona, Dávalos, others; article from La opinión de Sinaloa (January, 1863) telling of conspiracy of Dávalos, others, to assassinate Plácido Vega and to overthrow government of Sinaloa at instance of R. Corona.
- (1860; 1863) (Box 10, Folder 117)
  Documents by J.M. Flórez; official records; lists of men ill, numbers of soldiers to be replaced, lists of those recovered; disposition of men made, of officers in charge, etc. (1863). Similar reports for 1860.
- (October, November, 1861) (Box 10, Folder 118)
  Official records from prefecture of district of Fuerte submitted by C. Palomares. List of items distributed to men at Fuerte from government storehouse. Reports concerning discipline of men, of leaves granted, etc.
- Lists, district by district, of individuals with whom correspondence pending. (Box 10, Folder 119)
- (1860-1863) (Box 10, Folder 120)
  Correspondence: letters to Plácido Vega sorted by district, state, etc.
  - Tepic: letters to Plácido Vega from P. Ogazón, R. Valle, L. Tostado, J. Sepúlveda, others.
  - Cosalá: letters to Plácido Vega from R. Urrea, P. Aguilar, J. Villasenor, L. Ortiz, Francisco de la Vega.
  - Chihuahua: letters to Plácido Vega from governor of Chihuahua, others.
  - San Benito: letters to Plácido Vega from Santos Delgado, P. Lopez, others.
  - Álamos: official documents (inventory 1861;records of events transpiring in November, 1861;lists of expenses, etc.
  - Guaymas: letters to Plácido Vega from L Ávilez, F. Cervallos, P. Quintana, M. Urrea, others.
- Continuation of Folder 120 (Box 10, Folder 121)
  Correspondence: letters to Plácido Vega sorted by district, etc.
  - San Ignacio: letters to Plácido Vega from J.C.Hernández.